你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到沙箱模块的继续部分
welcome to the continuation of the sandboxing module
我是Yan，今天谈谈如何逃离seccomp
I'm Yan and I'm here to talk to you about seccomp specifically how to escape seccomp
我们见过很多例子
we saw a lot of examples of
两个关于如何设置seccomp的例子
well two examples of how do you set seccomp
一个对于进程本身，一个对于其子进程
one for the process itself one for its children
在最后一个视频中
in the last video today
这段视频我们要讲的是如何逃脱
this video rather we're gonna talk about how to escape
对于seccomp来说，这并不容易
from seccomp typically this is not easy
Seccomp非常好，它是一个现代的解决方案
seccomp is very good seccomp is a modern solution
我前面提到docker依赖于它
I mentioned previously that docker relies on it
Chrome依赖于它
chrome relies on it
Firefox 等很多产品
Firefox a lot of products
很多正经实用的程序依赖于seccomp提供的安全性
a lot of serious real deal programs rely on seccomp for security
所以它是非常优秀的
so it is very good
但有一个基本的事实
but there is this kind of fundamental truth
所有这些都依赖于seccomp的程序
that all of these things that rely on seccomp for security
他们需要提供服务
they need to do stuff
他们需要和用户交互
they need to uh interact with the user
需要与互联网交互
they need to interact with the internet
需要高性能
they need to uh do things performancely
这通常意味着
which often means
直接调用内核来实现功能
calling directly into the kernel to do stuff
使用系统调用而不是通过它们的父进程
using system calls um rather than going through their parent process
当然它们也需要与父进程通信
they also need to communicate with their parent process
这意味着，嗯，以某种方式通过内核进行交互
typically this means um interacting through the kernel in some way
嗯
um
所以实际上很难做一个不允许任何系统调用的沙盒
so it's actually very hard to make a sandbox that doesn't allow any system calls
通常你可以在沙盒中做一些事情
typically you have something that you can do in a sandbox
这就为攻击者提供了回旋余地
and this opens up some wiggle room for an attacker
今天要讲三种seccomp沙盒失效的原因
um we're gonna talk about three ways that uh seccomp base sandboxes might fail today
一是过度宽松的政策，二是混乱
one of them uh is overly permissive policies then confusion
三是内核漏洞，将在以后的课程细讲
and the 3rd one is kernel vulnerabilities you actually cover that in a future module uh more thoroughly
嗯
um
我们来谈谈宽松政策
let's talk about permissive policies right
系统调用很复杂
system calls are complex
它们的数量非常多
and there's an enormous amount of them
如果你看过我一直在讲的Ryan A. Chapman系统调用表
if you've looked at the Ryan A. Chapman system call table that I keep talking about
现代Linux系统上有超过300个系统调用
there are hundreds over 300 Linux system calls on a modern Linux system
还有越来越多的在不断被添加进去
and and more are added constantly
如果你调出一份现代的清单
if you pull up a modern list
我不知道Ryan A Chapman更的有多新
I don't know how up to date Ryan A Chapman is
但如果你调出一份现在的列表
but if you pull up a modern list
并且在您的计算机上尝试这些系统调用
and try some of these system calls on your computer
比如列表上后面的几个
like the later ones in the list
你的电脑应该不支持，因为
you won't have them on your computer because
它们太新了
they are too new
不断的有新linux版本，新功能出现
they're constantly  being added one or two Linux version to enable new functionality
而且
and
这意味着沙盒很难一直跟进系统新功能
this means that it's actually very hard to keep up with sandboxing them all properly
您有一个依赖于某些特定系统调用的沙盒
oftentimes you have a sandbox that might rely on some specific system call
但在一种特殊的模式下
but in one particular mode of it
所以你试着写一个seccomp沙盒
so you try to write a seccomp sandbox
它允许特定的系统调用
that allows specific configurations of system calls
但有些系统调用可能没考虑到
and some things might slip through
也可能只是担心拦截后会破坏你的程序
you might also just be worry of breaking your programs
像docker就需要启用很多的系统调用
something like docker actually requires quite a lot of system calls to be enabled
因为所有在docker容器内运行的程序
because everything that runs inside the docker container
都会继承父进程的seccomp配置
inherits the seccomp configuration of the parent
所以你不能把所有东西都禁止
so you can't just seccomp away everything
必须做取舍，留下一部分系统调用
you have to be reasonable and leave a lot of stuff open
有些docker漏洞是由于不正确的seccomp配置导致的
and there have been docker vulnerabilities arising from incorrect seccomp
过度宽松的seccomp配置
overly permissive seccomp configurations
一个非常著名的seccomp失效案例，不能说是一个漏洞
one very well known example of seccomp failure case not necessarily real vulnerabilities
尽管确实存在由此产生的漏洞
although there have been real vulnerabilities that are stems from this
是在沙盒进程中允许ptrace
is what happens when you allow ptrace in a sandbox process
ptrace是Linux的调试功能
ptrace is Linux's debugging functionality
您可以使用ptrace系统调用
you can use the ptrace system called
作为调试器附加到某个进程上
to attach to a process as a debugger
监视它的执行
to monitor its execution
改变内存，改变寄存器
to change memories change registers
可以获得完全控制权
you can take complete control obviously
你可以改变寄存器
you can change registers
您可以更改指令指针
you can change the instruction pointer
你可以通过改变内存来注入shellcode
you can inject shellcode by changing the memory
你可以执行任何你想执行的
and you can execute whatever you want right
如果你让沙盒进程使用ptrace
so if you let a sandbox process use ptrace
如果您的seccomp防火墙启动ptrace
if your seccomp firewall arouse ptrace
并且该进程有连接的权限
and that process has the permission to connect
它可以作为调试器附加到另一个进程
as it attaches debuggage to another process
就能通过另一个进程逃离沙盒
it can escape the sandbox through this other process
这是一个在CTF比赛中相当常见的沙盒逃逸方式
it's a it's a fairly common sandbox escape in the CTF world for example
嗯
um
有些系统调用有一些的不常见的疯狂效果，比如
uh there're also less known crazy effect of system calls for example
sendmsg系统调用不仅可以发送从文件中读取的数据，还可以发送
the sendmsg system call can send not just data that you read out of files but
打开文件描述符本身
the open file descriptor itself
嗯
um
当你在代码中执行open
when you do an open in your shell code
它返回文件描述符，数字3之类的做为标志
and it returns file descriptor three or whatnot for the flag
通常情况下，如果您将数字3发送到另一个进程
typically if you send that number three to another process
它只是一个数字3
it's just a number three
但是使用sendmsg可以发送包装好的元数据
but using sendmsg you can send that wrapped metadata
表明这是一个文件
that says hey this is a file
然后内核看到这个元数据，并将这个内核跟踪的打开文件传输
and then the kernel sees that metadata and transfers the concept of that open file which is tracked by the kernel
到您要发送消息的进程中
into the process that you're sending the message to
这是一个疯狂的功能但是它是存在的
which it's a crazy uh piece of functionality but uh it's uh exists and uh
所有这些例子实际上都是我在ctf中用过的
all these examples actually things I've used actively in C t F
所以它是作为一种漏洞存在
and so it exists as a as a vulnerability
嗯
um
使用PRCTL系统调用可以做很多疯狂的事情
there are crazy things that you can do with the prctl system call
就像这个抓包。你可以对进程做一些奇怪的事情
it's like this grab bag. a weird stuff you can do to a process
然后还有process_vm_write之类的东西
and then there's things like process_vm_write
该系统调用可以将内存直接写入另一个进程
this system call can write memory directly into another process that
你对这个进程只需要某种程度的权限
that you have um some level of access to
显然，你可以使用这个在特定的配置中逃离沙箱
obviously you can use this potentially in the right settings to also escape sandboxes
跟踪所有系统调用的所有功能并保证安全是很难的
it's hard to keep track of all of the functionality of of all of these system calls  securely
错误确实会发生
and and and mistakes do happen
我先把相机藏起来
uh let me hide my camera real quick
这样你们就能看清整句话了
so that you can see that whole sentence all right
很酷的
cool
继续
moving on
第二类叫做混淆
whole category number two system called confusion
这源于一个有趣的设计决策
this stems from an interesting design decision
我们讨论了很多AMD是如何使AMD 64向后兼容x86的
we've talked a lot about how AMD made AMD 64 backwards compatible with x86
可以对系统做出副作用很少的改变，运行x86代码
you can actually run x86 code basically on change with very few side effects
默认情况下包括所有的指令
and this includes by default all the instructions
大多数指令仍然处理32位代码32位数据
most of the instructions still deal with 32 bit code 32 bit data
有一个前缀能让指令使用64位数据
it's a prefix that makes them use 64 bit data and so on
Linux实际上支持32位和64位代码在同一个进程中交互运行
Linux actually supports 32 bit and 64 bit code running interchangeably in the same process
所以你的程序就像在一行和下一行之间
so your program like one between one line and the next or
实际上你可能得用汇编来实现
realistically you have to probably write this in assembly
在一个指令和下一个指令之间说，好的，好了
between one instruction in the next say okay that's it
我不用64位模式了
I'm done with 64 bit
我要转到32位模式了
I'm I'm moving to 32 bit mode
实际上，这样做是有原因的
there actually reasons to do this um
这是为了启用某些现在已经过时的沙盒功能
this enables certain other sandboxing functionality now obsolete
您可以了解一下，native client是沙箱的名字
you can look into native client was the name of the sandbox
它在内存对齐等方面做了一些技巧
that did some tricks with with memory alignment and so forth
但关键是这是有可能的
but the point is it's possible and
第二点，出于某种原因，我不明白
and the 2nd point for some reason I don't understand
让我再把相机关掉，这样你就能看到了
let me turn off my camera again so you can see
让我把自己移到上面
let me just move myself to the top
出于某种我不明白的原因
for some reason that I don't understand um
Linux对于x86和amd64有不同的系统调用定义
Linux has different system called definitions for x86 versus amd64
在amd64上使用系统调用指令有两种不同的方式来触发它们
there are two different ways to trigger them on amd64 use the syscall instruction
在x86上使用参数为128的中断指令，即0x80
on x86 to use the interrupt instruction with an argument of 128 in hextest one that is 0x80
根据你触发系统调用时内核所处的模式，它会使用不同的映射
and depending on how you trigger system calls into the kernel it uses different mappings
例如，在AMD 64模式调用exit系统调用的参数是60
for example in AMD 64 exit a system calls 60
在x86_32和x86模式，它的参数是1
on x86_32 bit x86 it is system call 1
让我给你看看这个
let me show you this
我写了一些shellcode
I have some shellcode written
这个调用exit，就是这样
this calls exit that's it
所以我要把它汇编一下
so I'm gonna assemble it
组成一个elf可执行文件
assembled it into an elf here
哦，现在我们可以执行了
oh now we can execute this
当然它只是退出
of course it just exits
我们可以用strace看一下
we can strace it
顺便说一下，strace也使用ptrace来完成它的工作
by the way strace also uses ptrace to do its job
就是这里
and here it is
我们再使用完全相同的方法执行exit
we do exit use the exact same thing
像我说的32位模式也没问题
like I said 32 bit mode no problem
改成EAX 1，然后我们执行INT OX80
we say EAX 1 and then we do INT OX80
汇编
assemble it
strace它，exit在这被调用了
strace it and there is our exit
实际上strace说哦哦哦
and actually strace says oh
我们运行的是32位模式
we're running in 32 bit mode
好吧
all right
就是这么简单
and it's that simple
如果你在x86中使用系统调用60会发生什么?让我们看看
what happens if you try system call 60 in x86 let's see
它是umask
it is umask
看，执行的根本就不是exit
see it's not exit at all
我为什么要说这些
why am I saying all this it's
因为当你写seccomp策略时
because when you write seccomp policies
我的意思是，让我们看一下上一集中的seccomp程序
I mean let's actually pull up our seccomp from the previous video
我们编写这个策略是为了将read系统调用添加到将被kill的系统调用列表中
we wrote this policy to add the read system call to a list of system calls that will be kill
或者更确切地说，创建一个规则，如果它匹配被调用的读取系统，它就会杀死进程
or rather to create a rule that if it matches the read system called it will kill the process
这将为AMD 64创建规则
this will create that rule  for AMD 64
实际上这些都是AMD 64的默认配置
in fact all these default configurations for AMD 64
好的事情是
the nice thing is
默认配置会杀死任何试图在32位模式下使用INT OX80指令的系统调用
the default configuration will actually kill any system calls that are attempted in 32 bit mode with the INT OX80 instruction
但有些非默认配置不是这样的
but there are non default configurations that are not like that
考虑在dockor容器中，您需要能够运行32位代码
consider inside your dockor container you need to be able to run 32 bit code
或者至少在默认情况下这是允许的
or at least by default this is allowable
这是一个常见的功能
and that's a common source of own abilities
如果我添加代码
if I add the code
我一下子就忘了代码是什么了
and I forgot what this code is off the top of my head
但如果我在这个过滤器中添加了允许32位系统调用的代码
but if I added code to this filter to allow 32 bit system calls
我没有特别添加一个规则来杀死32位版本的read
and I didn't specifically add a rule to kill the 32 bit version of read
这仍然是允许的
it would still be allowable
而且
and
这些错误确实会发生，漏洞也确实会出现
these mistakes do happen and vulnerabilities do arise
好吧
alright
让我们继续
let's move onwards to
内核漏洞
kernel vulnerability
所以这是越狱者的最后手段
so this is kind of the last resort of the jailbreaker
沙盒逃脱艺术家
the sandbox escape artist
如果沙盒配置良好
if the sandbox is well configured
将很难逃脱。Seccomp很好
it's very hard to escape.  seccomp is good
它有现代的好的功能，深受很多公司的信赖
it is the modern good functionality it is trusted by quite a lot of companies
如果它的安全参数使用得当，是无法逃脱的
when used properly it is inescapable with its security parameters
事情就像我说的seccomp沙箱
the thing is like I said every seccomp sandbox
在大多数情况下必须允许一些系统调用
for the most part has to allow some system calls
因为进程需要完成它们的工作
because processes need to do their job
这些系统调用由内核处理
and those system calls are handled by the kernel
内核接收到一些参数
so the kernel receives some arguments
然后它开始工作
and it starts doing work
内核并不完美
well the kernel is not perfect
内核实际上充满了bug
the kernel is actually full of bugs
所有的软件都充满bug
all softwares are full of bugs
内核不是一个例外，对吧
and the kernel is not an exception right
其中一些bug是可探索的漏洞
and some of these bugs are explorable vulnerabilities
其中一些可以在沙盒里通过系统调用触发
and some of them can be triggered through system calls that you can make from inside a sandbox process
这很强大，有很多沙盒逃脱方法
this is powerful there are a lot of sandbox escapes
沙箱不是一切的终点
sandboxing isn't the end all be all
它使漏洞利用过程复杂化
it complicates the exploitation process
但仅在2019年，就有超过30个chrome沙盒逃脱
but in 2019 alone there are like over 30 chrome sandbox escapes
你可以点击github链接
you can hit up that github link
里面有一个很棒的清单
um there's a really awesome list of all of them
记录的不仅仅是2019年，还有很多
um not just 2019 but but uh quite a lot
它们都有或者很多都写了笔记
and uh they all have or many of them have writeup that you can read
描述了这些漏洞以及它们是如何被利用的
that describe these  vulnerabilities and how they were exploited
当然关于内核漏洞本身
and for kernel vulnerabilities themselves of course
敬请期待，我们稍后会讲到
stay tuned we will be covering this later in the class
这是一个有趣的漏洞领域
um it is an interesting area of vulnerability
假设你还不是一个高级黑客
so let's say that you are not yet that advanced a hacker
您还没有到发现并利用内核漏洞的地步
you're not to the point where you're finding kernel vulnerabilities and exploiting kernel vulnerabilities
嗯什么
um what
你运气不好吗
are you out of luck
我的意思是
I mean
也许不是
maybe not
沙箱通常被设计用来限制代码执行
oftentimes the sandboxes they're designed to limit code execution
这并不总是你的目标
uh that's not always your goal
事实上，您的目标通常是窃取一些数据
in fact oftentimes your goal is to exfiltrate some data
尤其是所有这些题目
especially in all of these challenge problems
你想要窃取/flag
you want to exfiltrate slash flag
这是PWN学院的习题
right for the practice problems for pwn college
如果这是你的目标
if that's your goal
您可能不关心运行任意代码
you might not care about running arbitrary code
你可能不需要执行bin cat
you might not need to execute bin cat
你只需要
you just need to
找出一些关于flag的信息
get some information about the flag out
通常
and oftentimes
即使你不能直接得到这些信息
even if you can't get that information directly
如果正确的系统调用被禁止
if the right system call is banned
以及所有你能想到的用来写数据的系统调用
and all other system calls you can think of to write data
你仍然可以得到一些信息
you can still get some information out
比如，你可以调用sleep
right for example you might be able to call sleep
基于对sleep的调用
and based on calling sleep
您可以根据进程运行的时间来传递数据
you can communicate data based on how long your process was running
我没能确保我的相机不碍事
I did a bad job making sure my camera doesn't get in the way
放这里
here
您可能只能控制是否崩溃
you might be able to only control whether you crash or not
或者你是否崩溃或挂起或者其他一些1位的是或否信号
or whether you crash or hang or or some other one bit signal yes or no
但是你猜怎么着
but hey guess what
所有的数据都是由比特组成的
all data is made out of bits
如果你能在一次执行中传递一个比特
if you can communicate one bit in one execution
在下一次执行中，使用下一种方式来获得第2位
in the next execution you ride and next way to communicate the 2nd bit
然后是第三位，你们可以一位一位的获取数据
and then the 3rd bit and you can communicate bit by bit
嗯，还有其他的方法
um and there's other ways that there you know
如果没有崩溃，每个程序都会带着返回代码退出
every program exits with the return code if it doesn't crash right
这是你发送的数据
that is data that you are sending
你不需要直接通过文件描述符发送数据
uh you don't have to directly send data  over file descriptor
（不需要）通过标准输出来获取数据
over standard out  to get that data
一个现实中攻击者使用的迂回方法的例子
a real world example of kind of a round about way that attackers can use
在这种情况下，从网络中获取数据时
to get data out of networks in this case
通过域名服务查询避免过滤出站流量
to avoid filters on outbound traffic is through domain name service queries
假设我运行一个名为pwn.college的域名
right imagine I run a domain named pwn.college
并且我经营一个域名服务器
and I run a name server
这允许您解析pwn.college中的子域，比如
that allows you to resolve sub domains in pwn.college such as
csc466.pwn.college
当我利用你，在你的机器上放点东西
and when I exploit you and put something on your machine
我无法从那里访问网络
I can't get any network queries out from there
但我可以查询域名
but I can make domain name queries
这往往是一种实际情况
this is often an actual situation in fact
它的一个版本经常被用来突破WIFI付费限制
a version of this is often used to punch through WIFI pay walls
我可以查询
I can query something like
www.我想泄露出的密码123456.pwn.college
www.the password that I leaked is 123456.pwn.college right
它的解析结果或者说
and that resolve a resolution or that
这个查询将转到pwn.college
query will go to pwn.college
我会在服务器上看到一个查询
and I will see on my server a query for
我泄露的密码123456.pwn.college
the password that I leaked is 123456 .pwn.college
现在我知道了泄露的密码
and now I know it
这不是您应该使用的数据探索方法
this isn't the data exploration method you should use
我们实际上封锁了所有的出站网络连接
we actually blocked off all outbound network connections
别，这不是暗示什么的
don't this isn't the hint or anything
我只是说侧通道的概念
I'm just saying the concept of side channels
这是它的通称
it is the general term for this
它是网络安全的一个巨大研究领域
it is a big one. A huge research area in cyber security
一般来说只要你能获取1bit数据
typically as long as you can get out one bit of
你就有了一个非常强大的原语
then you have a very powerful primitive
好吧
alright
这就是seccomp的全部内容
that is it for abusing seccomp
感谢收看PWN大学
thank you for watching pwn college